<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The skilfull mountebanke. Or, Come, and I'le cure you It hath not so much power as patience, yet 'tis a playster for all sores. By Ioannes Baptista Guardano Lodovico puncto. A Frenchified Italian, and borne in Bucklersberry.</title>
            <author>Joannes Baptista Guardano Lodovico puncto.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845686</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10602</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10602)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The skilfull mountebanke. Or, Come, and I'le cure you It hath not so much power as patience, yet 'tis a playster for all sores. By Ioannes Baptista Guardano Lodovico puncto. A Frenchified Italian, and borne in Bucklersberry.</title>
                  <author>Joannes Baptista Guardano Lodovico puncto.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] O[kes] for Thomas Lambert and are to bee sold at his shop neere the hospitall gate in Smithfield, at the signe of the Horse-shooe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Joannes Baptista Guardano Lodovico puncto is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10602:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10602:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <p>The Skilfull Mountebanke. <hi>OR,</hi> Come, and I'le cure you.</p>
            <p>It hath not ſo much power as Patience, yet 'tis a Playſter for <hi>all Sores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Ioannes Baptiſta Guardano Lodovico puncto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Frenchified <hi>Italian,</hi> and borne in <hi>Backlerſberry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>I.O.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Lambert</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop neere the Hoſpitall gate in <hi>Smithfield.</hi> at the Signe of the Horſe-ſhooe, 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="list_of_cures">
            <pb facs="tcp:10602:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>The Names of <hi>the Cures.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Cure for Melancholy.</item>
               <item>2. A Cure for a maidens Timpany.</item>
               <item>3. A Cure for the Green Sickneſſe.</item>
               <item>4. A Cure for the Falling Sickneſſe in mans eſtate.</item>
               <item>5. A Cure for Cuckolds.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="compendium_of_medicinal_cures">
            <pb facs="tcp:10602:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>The Skilfull Mountebanke.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If any man be troubled with <hi>Melancholy,</hi> let him take this following Medicine.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F his Melancholy procéede by Love, the paſſion is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dangerous, and difficult to cure; the things that muſt bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the Remedy, are hard to come by.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Medicine.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Iuyce of thrée well mads (and as well told) Ieſts, applying them to the Patients ſpléene, that they may as it were tickle him; if he begin to laugh, there is ſome ſigne of Health:
<pb facs="tcp:10602:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->let him bee then forthwith carryed to a warme Bed, which muſt bee carefully made by a perfect Virgin of five and Thirty yéeres of Age, but very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and one whoſe Lip no man did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver touch ſince ſhee was five yeeres old. When the aforeſaid Bed is made, let this aforeſaid Virgin be cauſ'd to be put into it; but let mee tell you one thing by the way, you muſt leave them ſo; 'tis not a Ruſh matter for watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by him with a Ruſh-candle, he will be well enough by Morning, Ile war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, if he can ſweate upon't. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee riſes, you muſt provide this Cordiall for him: The ſtones of a Goate, the guts of Crabs, the braines of Sparrow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Monkies marrow, Pith of Oxen, with the yelkes of five new layd Egges, layd by an Henne of the Game: all theſe compounded together, if he may have the continuall company of his Virgin had fellow, will in one halfe yeere drive his Melancholy quite from him; if not, he is not a man of this World: Therefore wee'le ſpeake no more of him, but proceede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10602:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
               <head>If any Mayden bee ſicke of a Timpany, let her repaire to my Medicine, which is here ſet downe.</head>
               <p>IF this Virgin bee ſo ſicke of <hi>Cupid,</hi> that the Diſeaſe is come to a Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, let her with all ſpéede poſſible remoove her ſelfe to ſome old Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes houſe for Forty Weekes, where there is change of Ayre, keeping a ſpare Dyet as ſhee travailes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes after uſing lawfull exerciſes. till ſhee be married: Then if ſhe have any more Wit than ever any of her Sexe had, which is, to keepe her owne Counſell, ſhee is paſt all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: withall ſhee muſt have a great care, that the Tympany which ſhee left behinde her, come not in her Husbands ſight, leaſt it breede a worſe Diſeaſe: And ſo much for a Lympany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10602:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
               <head>A Cure for the Greene-Sickneſſe.</head>
               <p>IF any Virgin have made ſo little uſe of her Time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſhe is puniſhed with a diſeaſe call'd the <hi>Greene ſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ckneſſe,</hi> ſo that her colour beginnes to fade, and her fleſh is cover'd with a yellowneſſe, let her take my counſell: Firſt of all, let her forſake the former dyet ſhe uſ'd, which was to feede upon Sea coale Cyndars, Aſhes, Chalke, and Oate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale; loame wall, and parch'd Peaſe, Beanes, and dry Biſket; for unleſſe theſe cauſes be taken away, it is almoſt impoſſible that any Medicine ſhould worke upon her: then let her Father or Mother (if ſhe have any) provide for her a man of courage, full of mettall and very active: let her parley with him a little, if hee can take my counſell, hée ſhall quickly convert her pale colour to Red, and her Melancholy to laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 'tis not amiſſe, (if they can agrée
<pb facs="tcp:10602:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->together) if the Banes of Matrimony be ask'd betwixt them, ſhee'le bee the fitter to receive her Cure, and hee to play the Phyſitian; but if the Maide b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very farre gone, ſo that ſhee requires preſent helpe, let the Banes alone, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee'le goe a neerer way to worke: A Licence may be had, and 'tis a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> walke to <hi>Pancridge;</hi> if theſe Rules be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved, and if ſhee bee of a mild na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not froward, cholericke, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, but is contented to lye with him every Night without a Fée, in Forty Weekes the <hi>Greene Sickneſſe</hi> may bee converted to a chopping Boy, or a bouncing Girle, which will keepe her Ile warrant her, from ever having it againe: So much for the Greene ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If any mans Eſtate be troubled with the Falling Sickneſſe, let him hearken to mee.</head>
               <p>WHen a man doth firſt begin to be ſicke of this Diſeaſe, there
<pb facs="tcp:10602:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->there be a couple more that doe attend upon his body, which if they faſten, will hardly bee got off, and they are theſe: The one is called a <hi>Serjeant,</hi> the other a <hi>Yeoman,</hi> two ſuch dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Diſeaſes, that if hee be once but Encounter'd by them, hee is like to lye by it.</p>
               <p>This Falling Sickneſſe in a mans eſtate is very hard to cure, yet if it be let runne, 'tis tenne to one but that it comes to a worſe Diſeaſe, which is called a <hi>Rupture,</hi> but in plaine Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a <hi>Broke;</hi> which is a Diſeaſe, that if it have leave, will have ſuch power over him, that all the wiſeſt Glaziers in <hi>London</hi> ſhall ſcarre ſodder him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. And to ſay Truth, his hopes muſt bee, that hee may have a faire winde for <hi>Ireland,</hi> or elſe the Diſeaſe will periſh him: but if hee take my counſell, it ſhall never come to this: therefore marke my Advice; if hee be a Shop-keeper, let him keepe him to his Shop, kéepe truſty Servants and true Prentiſes, and let him avoyde the dangerous exerciſe of Ducking,
<pb facs="tcp:10602:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->leſt hee come home agen ſing'd like a Fire, Drake; 'tis a very ill ſigne of his thriving: Let him deale with honeſt men, and have a care his name be not to much us'd in other mens Bookes; let his faire Tongue and his faire dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling bée ioyn'd together, to invite good Cuſtomers, and a figge for the Falling Sickneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>If any marryed man bee troubled with a a paine in the Fore-head, let him looke out, for I have a Medicine for him.</head>
               <p>When a man is troubled with this Diſeaſe, 'tis a horrible ſigne that hee hath marryed a light Wife, and that being the greateſt cauſe of his Diſeaſe, it muſt (for ought I ſée) bée taken away from him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Cure can bée perfected, which (I muſt confeſſe) is; ſomewhat hard to performe; for they are grievances y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10602:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->will moſt commonly hang upon a man till they are even ready to hang them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that's more than a point next the worſt: Therefore the beſt counſell I can give him, is this; let him eate, drinke, and be merry; let him not ſhew himſelfe ſad and melancholly in company, leſt he give his Ieering ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies too much advantage o're him: yet hee's thus happy, he ſhall be ſure to be Ieer'd by none but the brethren of his owne company, and then hee may cry <hi>Cuckolds all arow,</hi> and make them mad that firſt thought to make him ſo: let him but make much of their wives, and kiſſe their children, the world wil ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke him a politick Whorema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, than a patient Cuckold, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation of the one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will controule the reproach of the other; and whereas he was before pittied for a wrong'd man, in this pittifull manner: 'Twas great pitty an honeſt carefull man ſhould have ſo ill a wife: They will ſay then, Let him alone, for Ile warrant, hee'le give her as good as ſhee brings. This is a report in this Age, more pleaſing
<pb facs="tcp:10602:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->to a man than the ſhamefull name of <hi>Cuckold:</hi> and when two Combatants wound each other equally, neither of them can boaſt the glory of the Battell: This is the ſureſt way for his Cure I thinke, and the ſureſt way to breake the heart of his wife; for wee are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, the firſt cauſe that made her ſo light heel'd, was to bee reveng'd upon him for ſome petty quarrell betwixt them, becauſe he would not let her ſée ſuch a Puppit-play, or ſome ſuch petty buſineſſe; perhaps he would not make her a Gowne of ſuch a new Stuffe as ſhe defir'd, but he breaking the necke of her revenge in this manner, 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poſſible that ſhee may very ſhortly and her daies in Melancholy like a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect envious perſon, deſtroying her ſelfe becauſe ſhe cannot kill another.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And if you think this Medicine wil procure</l>
                     <l>Your eaſe, you are welcome to the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kolds Curo.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if theſe doe your patience wrong,</l>
                     <l>Hearke, and I'le cure you with a Song.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb facs="tcp:10602:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
               <head>The Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ARe any Pooles that would be wiſe?</l>
                  <l>Are any falling that would riſe?</l>
                  <l>Is any rich that would be poore,</l>
                  <l>Ile purge his ſubſtance in an houre:</l>
                  <l>Is any bound that would be free?</l>
                  <l>Ile do't, let him repaire to me.</l>
                  <l>I come to cure what ere you feele</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Are any of their ſtrength beguil'd,</l>
                  <l>They cannot get their wives with childe?</l>
                  <l>If they be barren, they ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>Ile fit them with a remedy,</l>
                  <l>If once I take them in my hands,</l>
                  <l>They ſoon ſhal have more heirs then lands.</l>
                  <l>Then come to me what ere you feele</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10602:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
                  <l>If any Uſurer would have</l>
                  <l>A preſervation 'gainſt the grave,</l>
                  <l>Let him not yoke him to a Wife,</l>
                  <l>Ile promiſe him a longer life:</l>
                  <l>But if he marry, ten to one</l>
                  <l>Ile lay, he can be cur'd by none.</l>
                  <l>Yet come, Ile cure what ere you feels</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If any Lady would be proud,</l>
                  <l>That with no vertues is endow'd.</l>
                  <l>Ile puffe her with one praiſe or other,</l>
                  <l>Shall make her nicer than her Mother:</l>
                  <l>Such mighty power has my calling,</l>
                  <l>But not to keep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her pride from falling.</l>
                  <l>Then come to me what ere you feele</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If any Landroſſe be afraid</l>
                  <l>That ſhe ſhall loſe the name of Maide,</l>
                  <l>Yet not be married, let her be</l>
                  <l>Rid of that feare, and come to me;</l>
                  <l>Ile run the hazzard of a curſe,</l>
                  <l>She ſhall grow better, or elſe worſe.</l>
                  <l>Come then to me what ere you feele</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10602:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
                  <l>Hath any got a night diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>So that he cannot ſleepe for fleas?</l>
                  <l>Is any ſorrowfull or ſad,</l>
                  <l>Diſguiſed, Lunaticke, or mad?</l>
                  <l>Does any cutpurſe lye and linger</l>
                  <l>In torment for an itching finger?</l>
                  <l>He ſhall be cur'd by my expreſsions.</l>
                  <l>If he avoyd the quarter Seſsions.</l>
                  <l>Then come to me what ere you feele</l>
                  <l>Within, without, from head to heele.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10602:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
